Marvel Studios: Assembling a Universe is a documentary,
tv movie, fantasy film directed by None.
A look at the story behind Marvel Studios and the Marvel Cinematic Universe, featuring interviews and
behind-the-scenes footage from all of the Marvel films, the Marvel One-Shots and "Marvel's Agents of S.H.I.E.L.D."!
Self / Tony Stark / Iron Man, played by Robert Downey Jr..
Self, played by Clark Gregg.
Self, played by Scarlett Johansson.
Self, played by Kenneth Branagh.
Self, played by Hayley Atwell.
Self, played by Victoria Alonso.
The Marvel Cinematic Universe (MCU) centers on a series of American superhero films produced by
Marvel Studios based on characters that appear in publications by Marvel Comics.
The MCU is the shared universe in which all of the films are set.
The films have been in production since 2007, and in that time, Marvel Studios has produced and
released 37 films, with at least eight more in various stages of development.
It is the highest-grossing film franchise of all time, having
grossed over $32.4 billion at the global box office.
This includes Avengers: Endgame, which became the
highest-grossing film of all time at the time of its release.
The films are written and directed by various individuals
and feature large, often ensemble, casts.
Marvel Studios president Kevin Feige has produced every film in the franchise, while other Marvel Studios executives have also
produced some films alongside Feige, including the studio's former CEO Avi Arad for the first two releases.
Other individuals have also produced select MCU films, including Gale Anne Hurd for The Incredible Hulk; Amy Pascal for the Spider-Man films; Lauren Shuler
Donner, Ryan Reynolds, and Shawn Levy for Deadpool & Wolverine; and Anthony and Joe Russo for Avengers: Doomsday and Avengers: Secret Wars.
Marvel Studios releases its films in groups called "Phases".
Its first film is Iron Man (2008), which was distributed by Paramount Pictures.
Paramount also distributed Iron Man 2 (2010), Thor (2011), and Captain America: The First Avenger (2011), while Universal Pictures
distributed The Incredible Hulk (2008), which was co-produced by Hurd's production company Valhalla Motion Pictures.
Walt Disney Studios Motion Pictures began distributing the series with the
crossover film The Avengers (2012), which concluded Phase One.
Phase Two comprises Iron Man 3 (2013), Thor: The Dark World (2013), Captain America: The Winter Soldier
(2014), Guardians of the Galaxy (2014), Avengers: Age of Ultron (2015), and Ant-Man (2015).
Captain America: Civil War (2016) is the first film of Phase Three, and is
followed by Doctor Strange (2016), Guardians of the Galaxy Vol.
2 (2017), Spider-Man: Homecoming (2017), Thor: Ragnarok (2017), Black Panther (2018), Avengers: Infinity War (2018), Ant-Man
and the Wasp (2018), Captain Marvel (2019), Avengers: Endgame (2019), and Spider-Man: Far From Home (2019).
The first three Phases are collectively known as "The Infinity Saga".
The Spider-Man films are owned, financed, and distributed by Sony Pictures and
co-produced by Sony's Columbia Pictures and Pascal Pictures.
The films of Phase Four are Black Widow (2021), Shang-Chi and the Legend of the Ten Rings (2021), Eternals (2021), Spider-Man: No Way Home
(2021), Doctor Strange in the Multiverse of Madness (2022), Thor: Love and Thunder (2022), and Black Panther: Wakanda Forever (2022).
Phase Five comprises Ant-Man and the Wasp: Quantumania
(2023), Guardians of the Galaxy Vol.
3 (2023), The Marvels (2023), Deadpool & Wolverine (2024), Captain
America: Brave New World (2025), and Thunderbolts* (2025).
Deadpool & Wolverine was co-produced by Reynolds's and Levy's
respective companies Maximum Effort and 21 Laps Entertainment.
The Fantastic Four: First Steps (2025) begins Phase Six, and is followed by Spider-Man: Brand New Day (2026), Avengers: Doomsday
(2026), and Avengers: Secret Wars (2027), the latter two of which are co-produced by the Russo brothers's company AGBO.
The fourth, fifth, and sixth Phases are collectively known as "The Multiverse Saga", and also include
several television series and some television specials for the streaming service Disney+.